The "Tucsonians" Oral History Project collection, 1947-2002
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
The "Tucsonians" Oral History Project collection, 1947-2002, (bulk, 1999-2001)
MS 390
CCLPEP (California Civil Liberties Public Education Program) and the Coronado National Forest.
Collection includes the oral histories of several of the Japanese-American resisters of conscience who served sentences at the Catalina Federal Prison (renamed Gordon Hirabayashi Recreation Site in 1999) during WWII.
1 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
On December 7, 1941, the Japanese bombed Pearl Harbor, and soon afterward, President Franklin D. Roosevelt ordered the mass removal of 110,000 persons of Japanese ancestry from the West Coast to relocation camps located further within the United States interior. During this time, 1941-1943, Americans of Japanese ancestry were prohibited from serving in the US military. However, in 1944 the government re-instituted the draft for all Nisei, first generation Japanese born in America, including those in camps. Soon following, resisters of conscience were put on trial, most given 3 year sentences. A number of the resisters were sent to Tucson to serve their sentences, thus becoming the "Tucsonians". The "Tucsonian", is the self proclaimed name the group of American men of Japanese ancestry gave themselves while imprisoned in the Catalina Federal Prison on Mount Lemmon during the 1940s for resisting the draft. The "Tucsonians", and all wartime draft resisters, including the Nisei resisters were pardoned in 1947.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series
Series I: Interviews (includes audiotapes and transcripts)
Seroes II: Photographs
Scope and Content Note
Collection includes the oral histories of several of the Japanese-American resisters of conscience who served sentences at the Catalina Federal Prison (renamed Gordon Hirabayashi Recreation Site in 1999) during WWII. The collection contains audiotapes and transcripts of interviews conducted by representatives from the United States Department of Agriculture Forest Service from 1999 through 2002. The collection also includes photographs of the "Tucsonians" annual anniversary gathering. The oral history project was funded by CCLPEP (California Civil Liberties Public Education Program) and the Coronado National Forest.
Access Terms
California Civil Liberties Public Education Program.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Japanese Americans -- Interviews.
Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
Lemmon, Mount (Ariz.) -- History.
Gordon Hirabayashi Recreation Site (Mt. Lemmon, Ariz.)
Catalina State Park (Ariz.) -- History.
Coronado National Forest (Ariz. and N.M.)
Catalina Federal Prison (Mt. Lemmon, Ariz.)
Coronado National Forest (Ariz.) -- Santa Catalina Division -- History.
Container List
- Series I: Interviews (include audiotapes and transcripts)
  - Interviews: Release Form, 2002 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interviews: Gordon Hirabayashi interview tapes and transcripts, 1999, November 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interviews: Gordon Hirabayashi interview tapes and transcripts, August 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interviews: Group interview with Joe Norikana, Hideo Takeuchi, Ken Yoshida, and Harry Yoshikawa interview tapes and transcripts, 1999 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interviews: Takashi Hoshizaki interview tapes and transcripts, 1999 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interviews: Yosh Kuromiya interview transcripts (tape not present), 1999 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interviews: Joe Norikane and Tee Norikane interview tape and transcript, 2002 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interviews: Susumu Yenkida, Harry Yoshikawa, and Noboru Taguma interview tapes and transcripts, 2002 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interviews: Ken and Kay Yoshida interview tapes and transcripts, August 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interviews: Ken and Kay Yoshida interview tapes and transcripts, 2002May 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Photographs
  - Photographs: The "Tucsonians" Group Anniversary Photographs (incomplete run of dates), 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)